<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [

 <!-- RFC 2119 -->
 <!ENTITY MAY "<bcp14 xmlns='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'
   >MAY</bcp14>">
 <!ENTITY MUST "<bcp14 xmlns='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'
   >MUST</bcp14>">
 <!ENTITY MUST-NOT "<bcp14 xmlns='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'
   >MUST NOT</bcp14>">
 <!ENTITY OPTIONAL "<bcp14 xmlns='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'
   >OPTIONAL</bcp14>">
 <!ENTITY RECOMMENDED "<bcp14 xmlns='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'
   >RECOMMENDED</bcp14>">
 <!ENTITY REQUIRED "<bcp14 xmlns='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'
   >REQUIRED</bcp14>">
 <!ENTITY SHALL "<bcp14 xmlns='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'
   >SHALL</bcp14>">
 <!ENTITY SHALL-NOT "<bcp14 xmlns='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'
   >SHALL NOT</bcp14>">
 <!ENTITY SHOULD "<bcp14 xmlns='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'
   >SHOULD</bcp14>">
 <!ENTITY SHOULD-NOT "<bcp14 xmlns='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'
 >SHOULD NOT</bcp14>">
]>

<rfc category="info" docName="macaroon-mint" submissionType="independent">
  <front>
    <title>Macaroon minting service</title>
    <author initials="AP" surname="Millar">
      <organization abbrev="DESY">Deutsches Elektronen-Synchrotron</organization>
      <address>
	<postal>
	  <street>Notkestrasse 85</street>
	  <city>Hamburg</city>
	  <code>22607</code>
	  <country>Germany</country>
	</postal>
	<email>paul.millar@desy.de</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="9" month="February" year="2016"/>

    <keyword>macaroons</keyword>
    <keyword>bearer-token</keyword>
    
    <abstract>
      <t>Macaroons are bearer tokens that can include contextual
      caveats and support appending additional caveats after the token
      was issued.</t>

      <t>This document describes a simple API that allows a client to
      request a macaroon to be minted that encodes the client's
      authentication context along with zero or more additional
      caveats.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>In 2014, a group of six security researchers introduced the
      concept of macaroons with their paper "Macaroons: Cookies with
      Contextual Caveats for Decentralized Authorization in the
      Cloud".  In essence, a macaroon is a bearer token with the
      following properties: its usage may be restricted in any fashion
      that can be written as a text string, a macaroon may have
      multiple such restrictions.  An agent possessing the macaroon can
      further restrict its usage but cannot remove any existing
      restrictions, caveats may require the client to provide proof from
      some third-party.  Further details are available in the
      paper.</t>

      <t>This document describes how an authenticated client may
      request a macaroon to encapsulate their authentication context
      along with a set of caveats.  This macaroon may be used to
      authenticate as part of a login session, or may be delegated to
      a third-party.</t>

      <t>The client must be authenticated so that the macaroon is
      associated with the correct context.  How this authentication
      happens is outside the scope of this document.</t>
    </section>
    
    <section title="Requesting a macaroon">
      <t>The client requests that the server creates a macaroon by
      issuing an HTTP POST request to the path <spanx
      style="verb">/.well-known/macaroons</spanx>.  The request MUST
      have a <spanx style="verb">Content-Type</spanx> header with
      value <spanx
      style="verb">application/json</spanx>.  The request entity 
      must be a valid JSON object.</t>

      <t>The client MAY specify arguments that describe aspects of the
      desired macaroon in the form of one or more name/value pairs in
      the JSON object.  The letters in a name MUST be either only
      upper-case letters or only lower-case letters.  The server MUST
      process any request with a lower-case name that it does not
      understand as if the request did not contain that name/value
      pair.  The server MUST reject any request that contains an
      upper-case name that it does not understand.</t>

      <t>The following names are defined:
      <list style="hanging">
	<t hangText="CAVEATS">the value is a JSON list of String
	values.  Each JSON String is a caveat requested by the client.
	The client MUST NOT specify an empty list.  The server MUST
	either return a macaroon that includes all requested caveats
	or reject the request.</t>
      </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Server response">
      <t>In general, the server MUST respond to the HTTP POST requests
      with an HTTP response that has <spanx
      style="verb">Content-Type</spanx> header of <spanx
      style="verb">application/json</spanx>.  The entity in the 
      response is a valid JSON Object.</t>

      <t>The response JSON Object MAY include the following names:
      <list style="hanging">
	<t hangText="reason">the value is a JSON Object that provides
	human-readable description of the result.  The entries in this
	Object are messages in different languages.  The name is an
	RFC 5646 language tag and the value is a JSON String of the
	message in that particular language.  If the server includes a
	reason then it SHOULD include one entry using the <spanx
	style="verb">en</spanx> language tag.</t>

	<t hangText="invalid-caveats">the value is a non-empty JSON
	List of String values.  Each String value is a requested
	caveat that the server does not understand or is badly
	formatted.</t>

	<t hangText="macaroon">the value is a String value containing
	the minted macaroon.</t>
      </list>
      </t>
      
      <t>The server MUST reject requests from unauthenticated users
      with 401 Unauthenticated, as per RFC 7235.  The server MAY
      respond with 401 if the client has authenticated in a way that
      server policy rejects creating a macaroon but alternative
      authentication mechanisms exist with which the client could
      authenticate and the macaroon request would be accepted.</t>

      <t>The server SHOULD reject request with 403 Forbidden if the
      request comes from an authenticated client where the server
      policy rejects creating a macaroon for that user.</t>

      <t>The server MUST return 400 Bad Request if the client request
      contains the wrong <spanx style="verb">Content-Type</spanx>
      header value, or the request entity is not a valid JSON Object.
      The response MAY contain a JSON object with a informative
      reason.</t>
      
      <t>The server MUST reject any request that contains a caveat it
      does not understand or is badly formatted, failing the request
      with the 400 Bad Request status code.  The server SHOULD include
      the rejected caveats in the response JSON Object's
      invalid-caveats list.</t>

      <t>If the request is successful then the server responds with a
      200 OK status code.  The response MUST contain the <spanx
      style="verb">Content-Type</spanx> header with value <spanx
      style="verb">application/json</spanx>.  The response JSON object
      MUST have a <spanx style="verb">macaroon</spanx> name/value pair 
      containing the minted macaroon.</t>

      <t>The returned macaroon MAY contain caveats not requested by
      the user.  Such caveats may represent security policies that the
      server enforces, or may encapsulate the client's identity.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  
  <back>
    <!-- references -->
    <!-- section* -->
  </back>
</rfc>
